absolute Russification is underway There are a lot of
абсолютная русификация идёт Народа много
Circassian families among the people. I noticed that in the
черкесских семей Я заметил то что в
Chechen Republic the Chechen
Чеченской республике Чеченская
Republic it holds. Well, the Chechen
республика она придерживает Ну Чеченская
Republic is no longer the same, it is no longer the same,
республика она уже не та она уже не та
but still it is trying to maintain the
но всё равно она пытается придерживать
Chechen culture, the Chechen
чеченскую культуру чеченскую
nationality in Adygea, 3% of Circassians
национальность в Адыгее 3% черкесов
know the Adyghe language in Adygea in
знают адыгейский язык в Адыгее в
Republic of
республике
Adygea Hello, I'm from the city of Khmelny
Адыгея Здравствуйте я из города хмельни
You are
Вы
from the city of Maykop
откуда город Майкоп
Adygea Adygea you are a Circassian
Адыгея Адыгея вы черкес
Adyg neither Circassian nor Adyk And who is an Abaza
адыг ни черкес ни адык А кто абазин
Abaza is an Abaza - in principle, this is also
абазин так абазин - это в принципе тоже
Circassians, this is one ethnic group but
черкесы это одна этническая группа но
another on Well, well, Circassians anyway, that is,
другая на Ну ну черкесы всё равно то
well, you have a language  Adyghe is how
есть ну у вас язык адыгский так
it turns out
получается
Abaza Well, Abaza is a group of
абазинский Ну абазинский - это группа
Circassian languages, Adyghe or not, do you
черкесских языков адыгских или нет вы
understand the Adyghe, yes, I speak the Adyghe
понимаете да я разговариваю на адыгском
language, no, well, I mean, the Abaza people
языке вс не ну имею в виду вот абазины
understand the Adyghe language completely and the
да понимают адыгский язык полностью и
Adyghe people do
Адыги
not understand it completely, there are some
понимают не полностью есть некоторые
similarities, some words are
схожести некоторые слова полностью
completely different Well  I understand because I
абсолютно другие Ну я понимаю так как я
myself am a native speaker of this and that language is
сам носитель того и того языка исть
Well, it’s easy for me to understand. If I’m not mistaken, yes, then
Ну мне легко понял я Если не ошибаюсь да
I’ll check that now, yes. Or is this an
то это я сейчас проверю да Или это же
Adyghe group? Well, it turns out from
адыгская группа это ж получается у
the Abazas - these are the ones that were chronicled by the
абазины - это те что были летописные
Abazas, also they were also written by the Abaza Abazas  yes
абаз тоже их ещё писали абаз абаз да
They used to write Yes, the country the country was
Раньше писались Да страна страна была
Abaza and then the Abazas came from the Abazas, the
абазе а потом произошли от абаз гов
Abazas were also the Asil tribe,
произошли абазины было также племя асил
and the Abkhazians came from the Apsi there were two more
а от апси произошли абхазы было ещё два
tribes, but I’m sorry, I don’t remember the name,
племени но извиняюсь нени назову не
I understood yes And what are you talking about here? And
помню понял да А о чём тут общаетесь А я
while I’m
пока
singing, I’m just
пою так просто время
stretching out time  so why are you
растягиваю так за А зачем вы
stretching out the
растягивается
time to sleep I don’t want to understand So
время спать не хочу понял Так
Azin is one of the autonomous autochthonous
азин так один из автономных автохтонных
peoples of the Caucasus Chava
народов Кавказа Чава
Circassia so
Черкесия так
related now I’m interested
родственный сейчас мне интересно
so yes the Abaza language yes it
так да язык абазинский да отдельный
stands out separately Yes the Abkhaz Adyghe group of
выделяется Да абхазо адыгская группа
languages ​​yes that is it is related to the Adyk
языков да то есть он родственный адык
language yes but it is separate  The language is definitely
скому да но это отдельный Язык точно я
something I thought, yes, that the Abazins are
что-то я думал да что абазины - это
Adygs, just a subtype, it’s cool, and
Адыги просто подтип прикольно так А
how many? Yes,
сколько
few In Russia, few, yes And in the world,
Да мало В России мало да А в в мире
some in the world, in the
некоторые в мире в
world, well, as the Internet writes up to a million
мире ну как пишет интернет до миллиона
people Well, yes, the Internet writes that the prizes are
человек Ну да интернет пишет что призи
50 But  like an estimate of up to a million takes into account
50 Но типа оценки до миллиона учитывает
the number of the diaspora and the number of
численность диаспоры и численность
Akhads. The fact is that many of these
ахадов Дело в том что ээ многие вот эти
Adyghe Circassian Abaza peoples.
адыгские черкесские абазинские народы
After the conquest of the Russian
Они же после завоевания Российской
Empire, they moved to the territory
Империи переселились на территорию
after Russian imperialism.
после российского империализма народ
very
понял интересно на Кстати мне очень
nice, you are the first person on the Internet
приятно вы первый человек в интернете
who knows who the Abaz are, I know a lot of
которые знает кто такие абаз я много
nationalities, I study. My profession is
народности знаю изучаю У меня профессия
so
такая
nice. I’m a professional dog. I’ve already had
приятно Я профессиональный псок лет уже
practice for years. In a year, it will be
практики через года будет
simple, even well, in Adygea, what is your
то просто даже ну вот в Адыгее кто ты по
nationality? I say, Well, I say, I’m a
национальности Я говорю Ну я говорю я
Bazin.  this is who Well, I’m not talking about the
базин а это кто Ну это я не говорю про
Russians I’m talking Well, even about the Circassians
русских Я говорю Ну даже про адыгов
The Circassians don’t know who the locals are, they don’t
Адыги не знают кто такие местные не
know who the Abazas are Well, I, well, I’m
знают ккто такие абазины это Ну я ну я
not saying anything Well, too, the Russian
ничего не говорю Ну тоже Российская
Empire, it always erases it, it brings everyone under the
империя она стирает всегда она всех под
Russification umbrella Yes, and
коток русификации вносит Да и
firmly  absolute Russification is underway There are
прочно абсолютная русификация идёт
a lot of Circassian families. I noticed
Народа много черкесских семей Я заметил
that in the Chechen Republic the Chechen
то что в Чеченской республике Чеченская
Republic it holds the Nuna
республика она придерживает Ну нская
Republic it is no longer the same it is no longer the same
республика она уже не та она уже не та
but still it is trying to maintain the
но всё равно она пытается придерживать
Chechen culture the Chechen
чеченскую культуру чеченскую
nationality in Adygea 3% of Circassians
национальность в Адыгее 3% черкесов
know the Adyghe language in Adygea in
знают адыгейский язык в Адыгее в
Republic of
республике
Adygea And I am very offended by the fact that in
Адыгея И мне очень обидно за то то что в
the nineties after the collapse of the Soviet
девяностые годы после распада Советского
Union, the Chechens tried to give up their
Союза чеченцы пытались отдать свою
independence, and the Adygs, as soon as they sat down, they
независимость а Адыги как присели они
sit for this. You know what
так и сидят вот за это Зна знаете в чём
else is going on? Yes, the fact is that,
дело ещё получается Да дело в том что
uh, Chechnya is a
ээ Чечня
more mountainous territory  so there Yes,
более Горная территория так и там вот Да
if you look at the time of the conquest of the
Если смотреть во времён ээ завоевания
Russian Empire by the Soviet Union here in the
Российской империи Советский Союз сюда в
Krasnodar Territory, the Circassian Lands are
Краснодарский край черкесские Земли по
very
очень
much not autochthonous Yes, the Adyghe
ноде не автохтонных Да адыгского
population and it
населения и
turns out that they drove their population
получается и они вбивали своё население
here, they drove
сюда они вбивали
in the Russian population, they captured
ву российское население они захватывали
forts, they built forts, they founded
форты они строили форты они основывали
capitals are also on the Circassian lands and that
столицы ещё и на черкесских землях и то
is, these people They took root, that is,
есть этот народ Они прижились то есть
some said the elders, they said
некоторые сказывали старши они говорили
that some people They are alive with the
то что некоторые люди Они жива с
Circassian people And lived with them Alone
черкесским народом И жили с ними Наедине
on the same wavelength, that is, we said the
на одной волне то есть говорили мы
Circassians And some, on the contrary, imposed
черкесы А некоторые наоборот навязывали
Russian culture and then  there are also those Circassians.
русскую культуру и то есть и те черкесы
They suited her and at that
Они подобались ей и в то время в то
time, just like in Russia in the Russian
время вот как в России в Российской
Empire it was popular to learn
империи было же популярно учить
French, and in Circassia at that
французский язык а на Черкесии в то
time it was popular to learn the Russian
время было популярно учить российский
Russian language, and that is, even then it was already
русский язык и то есть и тогда была уже
from that time  before the start of the war and
с того времени даже до начала войны и во
during the war there would have already been
время войны уже бы
those of the North Caucasus. Well, I don’t know about
те Северного Кавказа Ну не знаю насчёт
that, I don’t know whether there was Russification before
этого не знаю то или была русификация до
that because, in principle, it
этого потому что в принципе всё равно
was still connected religiously and literary, it
связано было религиозно литературно это
was all connected with your east and not with
всё было связано с востоком у вас а не с
Russia in the east. Yes, and  Circassia
Россией востоком Да и Черкесия это была
was the only country in the North
это была единственная страна на Северном
Caucasus that until recently
Кавказе которая до последнего
refused Islam, since Islam the
отказывалась от Ислама так как Ислам у
Circassians have their own set of laws of the Khabza, and that
черкесов свой свод законов хабза и то
is, and some, that is, well, how can I say
есть и некоторые то есть ну как сказать
this, the rules in Islam? They did not coincide a little
так правила в исламе Они немного не
with the Khabza, and that is, They
совпадали с хабза и то есть Они до
the latter they are not Well, it’s not only the
последнего они не Ну так это не только у
Circassian thing, but all peoples Yes, they had their
черкеса дело что у всех народов Да были
own beliefs, their own rules, their
свои какие-то верования свои правила
own traditions Yes and uh Yes, and just like, for
свои традиции Да и э Да и так же как
example, Christianity
например христианство в Европе
was implanted in Europe, Islam was also implanted in
насадилась также Ислам на садился во
many regions of Asia and the Caucasus and  in
многих регионах Азии и Кавказа и в
some, let’s say, different nations have different
некоторых скажем у разных народов разные
remnants of the previous ones. For example, if the
остатки преды Вот например если возм у
Persians have some Tajiks, they still
персов там у каких-то таджиков и дальше
have the holiday Navruz, and many nations
есть праздник Навруз и у многих народов
have Navruz, it’s like a day, in my opinion,
есть Навруз это как бы день по-моему
if I’m not mistaken,
если я не ошибаюсь весеннего
they have the spring solstice, yes, that is
солнцестояния у них да то есть
Islam
мусульманство
that the cell of the body is the
что ячея тело в
adoption of Islam too You had your own
том принятия Ислама тоже У вас были свои
beliefs so yes, in what century did we
верования так да у нас в каком веке
accept
приняли
Islam if I’m not mistaken this is the 15th century if
ислам если я не ошибаюсь это XV век если
I’m not mistaken G It’s very late, it doesn’t
я не ошибаюсь Г Это очень поздно не Мне
seem to me that now it’s all right
кажется что сейчас ну се посмо
I’m already interested
Мне аж интересно
yes  so the spread of Islam in Circassia
да так распространение ислама в Черкесии
began in the 14th-1st centuries under the influence of the
началось в 14-1 веках под влиянием
Golden Horde and later the Ottoman Empire.
Золотой Орды А позже Османской империи
However, Islam was finally
Однако окончательно мусульманство на
established in the Northern Western Caucasus in the
Северном Западном Кавказе утвердилось в
centuries.
веках де Да но довольно бли да я думал
our
отрекайтесь как сказать упрекает наши
laws, that is, well, Islam is
законы то есть ну Ислам -
like our religion That's what
это как бы религия наша будет Вот так
they said Uh-huh,
они сказали Угу
I understand correctly that your
понял я правильно понимаю что у вас ваш
language is no longer studied in schools, even whatever it is, it’s just
язык уже в школах не изучается даже как
not like in school there’s mathematics
просто не то что в школе там математика
in m. That is, it’s not even studied  it’s just
на м То есть даже не изучается просто
that the Abaza language is there in the lower
там абазинский язык там в младших
grades, the Abaza language I don’t know the
классах абазинский язык я не знаю
Abaza language. Basically this is the territory of the
абазины В основном это территория
Karachay-Cherkess Republic, here in
карачаево-черкеской Республики здесь в
Adygea they study the Adyghe language. I study the
Адыгее изучают адыгейский язык Я изучаю
Adyghe languages ​​at school, and besides and in the
адыгейский язы в школе и помимо и на
street at school, yes, I was at school.
ули в школе да вот был у меня в школе
No way  like yes, like folklore like yes,
Никак это типа да как фольклорно типа Да
absolutely not studied at all, it’s just
абсолютно никак не изучается он просто
some works in Russian
какие-то произведения на русском языке
translated not into not into the Circassian language
переведённые не в не на черкесском языке
no study of the alphabet nothing
никакой не изучение алфавита ничего
no rules absolutely nothing just a
никаких правил абсолютно ничего просто
lesson in reading works in Russian let’s
урок читания произведений на русском
translate the Circassian language I learned
переведём Черкесский язык Я выучил
while not being Circassian  on the street in
будучи не черкесов на улице в
conversations and that is, well, of course, I have my
разговорах и то есть ну мне конечно то
own language I can say I can
есть свой язык я могу сказать я могу
say boldly I can say I don’t know
сказать смело я могу сказать я не знаю
Well, relatively speaking, I don’t know because
Ну условно Я не знаю потому что
first of all I have no one to talk to I have no
во-первых мне не с кем разговаривать У
except us here in
меня нету Вот кроме нас вот в
Maiko no no one person is his
Майко нету нет один человек есть это
father’s friend
отца друг
Well, he’s the same, he’s also from the Karachay-Cherkess Republic, they also
Ну он такой же он тоже с КЧР они тоже
also their family came here, but
также их семья сюда приехала но семья
his family went back there, he’s the only one
его там обратно уехала он один здесь
left here, that’s all here, no Azino here is Circassian and
остался всё тут нету Азино тут черкесс и
that is, it’s not convenient for them to speak the
То есть им не удобно разговаривать на
Circassian language  I have
черкесском языке Я имею
communication skills with people
коммуникабельность с людьми
and this is
и это
practical and many are surprised even
практично и многие удивляются даже
when there is such a joke that when someone
когда тут есть такой прикол то что когда
comes up to you and that you are a Caucasian,
к тебе подходит ви что ты кавказец тебя
they ask you from the East Kazakhstan region, they basically say, That
спрашивают ВКО в основном говорят То
is, you are
есть ты
an Adyghe I always answer that no And
адыгеец Я всегда отвечаю то что ха нет И
people all people are always surprised  when I
люди все люди всегда удивляются когда я
say no they say How do you say
говорю нет они говорят А как ты говоришь
no in the Adyghe language, that is, well, you
нет на адыгейском языке то есть ну ты
say you are Circassian no in Adyghe I
говоришь ты черкес нет на адыгейском я
speak with Abaza they are like How do you
говорю с Абаза они такие А как ты на
speak Adyghe Well I say I
адыгейском разговариваешь Ну я говорю я
learn them They say why Well I speak in
выучи Они говорят а почему Ну я говорю в
Aey  I live, I must know this language
аее живу я должен этот язык
Well, my mother is Circassian and
зна Ну и мать у меня черкешенка и за
due to this And my relatives are here, uh,
счёт этого И вот моя в родня тут э
exactly our family,
именно наш род
we have four households in our family and three
э у нас четыре двора в нашем роде и три
of the four households remained in the Karachay-Cherkess Republic What does
двора из четырёх остались в КЧР Что
family household mean? Yes, there is one family  surname and
семьи Да семьи есть одна фамилия и
several households in our surname, four
несколько дворов в нашей фамилии четыре
households, that is,
двора
well, these are people who are in fact
это то есть ну это люди которые по факту
relatives to you But they are so
тебе родственники Но они настолько
far away, they just bear your
далеки просто ну носят твою
surname My relatives, who are right here, have a
фамилию Моя родня которая именно здесь
very long history Why we
там очень долгая история Почему мы
live in Adygea, I can tell you, but
именно в Адыгее живём могу рассказать но
I’m up to now  I’ll tell you and let’s find it
я сейчас до расскажу и давай
interesting
интересно
and My family all speak the
и Моя родня вся разговаривает на
Circassian language, everyone speaks Circassians and
черкесском языке все говорят черкесы и
only
только
me and my father we say that we are
я с отцом мы говорим то что мы
Abas, everyone says that we
абазы все говорят то что мы очень много
were a lot And on the street I had arguments because of
было И на улице у меня были споры из-за
this when I spoke they told me  like
этого когда я говорил мне говорили типа
What is your last name I say so and
Какая у тебя фамилия Я говорю такой-то
so he says But this is your brother
такой-то он говорит А вот это твой брат
I say Well yes So you say you are
Я говорю Ну да Так ты же говоришь ты
Abas and he is a Circassian I say he is not a Circassian
Абас а он черкес Я говорю он не черкес
he says that he is a Circassian but he is an Abaza he
он говорит что он черкес но он абазин он
says No I  call him now, he’ll
говорит Нет я ему сейчас позвони он
say he’s Circassian and he’ll say so, and all his
скажет он черкес а он так и скажет и Вся
relatives will say that, everyone says that they’re
родня так скажет все говорят что они
Circassian. Everyone says that we’re with the
Черкес Все говорят то что мы у
Adyghe people, but we’re not. And now I’m
адыгейского но мы не А теперь
telling you why we
рассказываю Почему как мы здесь
ended up here,
оказались
mine, it was a long time ago, it’s my grandfather’s.
мой это было ещё давно это моего деда
If not
Если не
I’m mistaken, grandfather, even so He, I don’t remember what
ошибаюсь дед даже так Он я не помню что
he did But he was sentenced to
он сделал Но он был приговорён к
death, he was sentenced to death
расстрелу он был приговорён к расстрелу
and he had an only sister
и у него была единственная сестра
And this grandfather had children But my
А у этого деда были дети Но вот моего
grandfather’s father and his brothers and their father were
деда отец и его братья и их отца
shot And the children should have been shot  give it to the
расстреляли А детей должны были отдать в
orphanage and his sister so that the children would not be
приют и его сестра чтобы детей не
taken to the orphanage, she changed her last name,
забрали в приют поменяла фамилию
came to Adygea and said that we are
приехала в адыгею и сказала то что мы
from here, we are
отсюда мы
Circassians so that the children would not be taken away
черкесы чтобы детей не забрали
and my great-grandfather, well, that is, we have
и мой прадед ну то есть у нас есть
a cemetery in the village, everything is there. Well, relatives
кладбище в ауле там все Ну родственники
lie and everyone has one  surname and only that of my
лежат и у всех одна фамилия и только у
great-grandfather. The surname is spelled correctly
прадеда Правильно написана фамилия
because that’s what he is, well, as soon as he
потому что он таким он ну он сразу как
came here, he changed his surname back
сюда приехал он обратно фамилию
and now I’m 20 years old, when I
поменял и вот сейчас я в 20 лет я когда
change my passport, I want to
паспорт менять буду я хочу свою Ну
write my real surname because, well,
настоящую фамилию написать потому что ну
under the surname whose surname is  the one whose last name
под той фамилие которой под той фамилие
I go by is Well, it doesn’t exist in
которой я хожу её Ну не существует по
fact, you can just say
факту её просто можно сказать А как ты
Whose
считаешь чей
Crimea is Crimea historically or by modern
Крым Крым исторически или по современным
standards I asked
меркам Я задал
a question Well, I’ll take it from afar historically
вопрос Ну возьму издалека исторически
Crimea Tatars then
Крым татары потом
Circassians then Russia well for me Crimea
черкесы потом Россия ну для меня Крым -
is Ukraine I
это Украина
just understood  me Crimea is Ukraine It’s
понял просто для меня Крым - это Украина
just that when the Crimea began, I realized the thing is
Просто когда начина кры я понял дело в
that uh when they say there
том что ээ когда вот там говорят
originally Crimea Russia originally Crimea
изначально Крым Россия изначально Крым
Tatars The thing is that uh if you take it
татары Дело в том что ээ если брать
initially yes then it was Greek for
изначально да то он был греческим ещё
years there and so on, that is, but by the way
там годки и так дальше то есть но кстати
Circassians  uh, at one time they
черкесы э в своё время они
controlled Well, not all of Crimea They didn’t
контролировали Ну не весь Крым Южную
control the southern part
часть не контролировали
But the mainland majority Yes,
А материковую большинство Да
they controlled, in my opinion, there was Great
контролировали по-моему там была Великая
Circassia Yes and Circassia And by the way, from that
Черкесия Да и Черкесия И кстати с того
moment on, the Crimean Tatars are a lot of
момента Крымские татары очень много
Tatars living Well, on the current
Татаров живущих Ну на нынешней
territory of Circassia, many of them speak very much  the
территории Черкесии они многие очень
Circassian language and
разговаривают на черкесском языке и
a lot of them belong to the Circassians.
очень много из себя принадлежат черкеса
Well, the fact is that the Crimean Tatars have the
Ну Дело в том что у Крымских Татар есть
Crimean Tatars also have several
у Крымских Татар есть тоже несколько
ethnic subgroups that
этнических подгрупп которые
were formed alone with a component,
формировались одни с компонентом
for example, there were these Kipchaks
например там это были вот эти кипчаки
alone with a large Circassian component there and
одни с большим компонентом там
different peoples mixed there
черкесским та смешивались там разные
Yes  it was with the Goths and so yes yes yes it
народы Да было с готами и так
was like that, well, I’m also history and
да да да было такое ну я тоже история и
And who are you studying for
А ты на кого учишься
nationally I’m a full-time lawyer I’m now I’m up to studying I’m leaving
национально я фак юрист я сейчас я я до
Russia I understand you want to be a
учусь Я уезжаю с России Поня ты хочешь
lawyer like yes I
юристом типа быть
understand the Bar Ok, let’s run further than all the
понял Хорошо давай побегу дальше всего
good things for you  Let's all the best in
хорошего тебе Давайте всего хорошего
peace and
мира и
freedom. This is a lawyer,
Свободы Вот это юрист
this is a new channel of PDHI on Nyogo right now.
це новый канал пдши на нього прямо зараз
Having set the dialer to remove the fistula,
Постав дзвоник щоб отримати ус свище
we will
будем на
call L
зв'язку L